Uh, servers must not use elicitation to
request sensitive information from the
user. Must not do that, guys. Seriously,
guys, don't do that. Please don't do
that. Yeah, that's [music] exactly what
we're going to do.
>> Best part of when you can just, you
know, critical thing, right?
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, dude.
>> All right, hackers. Look, we got a lot.
I don't I don't know if you guys know
this, but there's a lot more to CTV than
just the podcast. Okay, I'm just going
to list a couple things you guys might
be interested in real quick. Okay, we
got the Discord. That's where a lot of
awesome conversations are happening.
This cool research channel in particular
is amazing on the Discord. We've got the
full-time hunters guild for those of you
making over 100k a year in bug bounty.
If you're looking to be around other
elite hackers, that's the place to do
it. We've got the critical thinkers tier
on the Discord. That's where we uh
that's like our inner circle. That's
where we share all of our scripts, do
exclusive AMAs, master classes, that
sort of thing. And we've got the
research lab over at lab.ctb.show
where if you've got a piece of research
you'd like to submit, you can submit it
there and we may take it hosted on the
blog and cover it on the pod for you.
Um, also underappreciated, but we also
have the swag store, guys. So, hit the
swag link over at ctbb.show
and you guys can buy some cool t-shirts
uh with critical thinking um you know,
slogan and stuff like that on it. All
right. Um, with that, let's go back to
the show. Check out some of those
things. All right. We're going to go
back to the show, but check out those
things for me. All right. Let's go.
[snorts]
All righty, hackers. So, here's the deal
today. All right. We had a whole episode
planned, but both of my co-hosts are
either sick or traveling for live
hacking events or both. Um, so it's just
going to be me today. And what do we do
when we're doing an impromptu episode by
yourself? We do an RFC deep dive, right?
Okay, let's go. We got model context
protocol this time. Um, and essentially
lately I've been kind of looking at this
because of some of the targets I'm
looking at and I think it's a really
relevant target uh for a lot of hackers
that are moving into the AI um
pentesting space. Um, and it's just
something to be a little bit more aware
of as well as you see those assets
around um people spinning up MCP servers
left and right. Um, so what I'm going to
try to do today is give you guys a good
overview of model context protocol MCP
and uh give you an idea of how the
protocol works uh what the general
architecture is, the authentication and
then we're going to dive a little bit uh
into uh the back and forth uh of the
communication of the protocol and the
various objects um that are being tossed
around. Okay, so let's go ahead and do
it. Um first up, let's go ahead and
discuss the architecture. So um well
actually before we this do this let me
preface I have spent probably cumulative
16 hours probably researching this this
uh protocol. Okay, so I'm not professing
to be like some mega expert on it, but I
can read a spec and tell you guys where
I think the problems are uh from a
security perspective. And uh you know,
if I'm looking at the results that I've
gotten from pentesting on some of these
things, um my hunches are often correct.
So, uh, this is definitely not claiming
to be a holistic assessment of MCP
threats, uh, threat model, but, um, I
think it will give you guys a good
starting spot to to kind of bounce off
off of as you go after these, um, uh,
MCP servers or clients. So, let's go
ahead and jump into that. Um, first
talking about the architecture, there
are MCP clients and MCP servers. There's
also some other pieces like MCP proxies
and authentication um, servers and stuff
like that. But for the purpose of this
podcast, we're going to focus mostly on
MCP servers and MCP clients. Okay. Um
these are communicating over uh JSON
RPC. So it's very readable, very
friendly. Um you can take a look at uh
the raw protocol very simply. I actually
wrote a malicious MCP client and server
um very easily in Python just by like uh
you know printing statements out and
reading statements in. Um so very
friendly protocol to look at from that
perspective. Um the the transport
mechanism is typically done over one of
these three um things. We've got uh
standard IO. So that's what I was just
mentioning a second ago where you can
print data to screen uh you know receive
data via a standard in and do your
communication that way. Um, there are
two other ones, streamable HAP and the
older HTTP serverside events. Um, I
haven't played around with these as
much. The one only ones I've looked at
have been, um, standard IO. So, um, you
know, but that's something to be aware
of for sure. Um, authentication. Okay,
now this is kind of where my gap of
knowledge comes comes in here. Um, the
client and server that I was looking at
um, used an alternative mechanism for
uh, authentication. So, I haven't spent
a lot of time assessing the
authentication in these uh servers and
clients, but I did read over the spec
and noticed a couple things that are
interesting. One, uh I want to read a
quote from the spec. Uh well, I guess
I'll say first uh ooth is one of the
mechanisms that they use for
authentication uh in MCP protocols. You
can read that whole spec uh there if
you're interested in going deeper on
that. But one of the quotes that stood
out to me was MCP clients and
authorization servers should support the
OOTH 2 dynamic client registration
protocol which exposes a lot of attack
surface. Um there's been um SSRF type
vulnerabilities in that functionality
before. Um the should in in this uh is
pretty strong. So uh I definitely think
we'll see dynamic client registration in
some of these MCP servers or clients and
authentication servers. Um so that could
be a good place to look. Also in section
3.3 under communication security we have
the following quote. Um implementation
uh implementations must follow the oath
2.5 section 1.5 communication security
spec. Specifically all authorization
servers uh must be served over HPS and
all redirect URIs must be either local
host or HTPS. And whenever we see
something like a caveat there local host
I always think like uh how are they
determining whether it's local host or
not? um you know that gives lots of
wiggle room for um different encodings
of IPs um DNS like contains uh or maybe
it starts with local host something like
that. So those could all be good things
to check on that front. Um all right so
moving past authentication we're going
to talk about the initialization flow
now and then we'll go into the various
um RPCs that can be utilized to incur
different actions on both the client and
the server. Okay. So, uh, initialization
is the process, uh, the H handshake
process that the client and the server
go through, um, when establishing
communication. So, the way that that
normally works is the client will send
an initialize RPC request to the server.
It will contain the protocol version,
capabilities, and client info, and then
the server will respond with the
initialization response to the client.
It will contain the protocol version,
the capabilities, the server info, and
one cool instructions field, which we'll
talk about in just a sec. So, let's go
ahead and dive a little bit deeper into
uh what that initialization uh component
for the client looks like. Um so,
pivotally, the thing that I mentioned
that it communicates obviously protocol,
version, and client info are important,
but not quite as much um as
capabilities. Okay. Um, capabilities uh
lets the server know what kind of um uh
well capabilities the client has access
to. Um, and there are three options
currently defined in the spec. Roots,
sampling, and elicitation. And we'll
cover all of those later. Um, there's
also a subscribe and list changed um
attribute beneath the capabilities for
each one of these. So, you know, roots,
list changed, true, subscribe, true. Um
and that supports whether you can get
notifications etc.
Okay. So you know if you're an MPC uh MC
MCP server you're going to receive a
JSON RPC from the client and it's going
to contain some set of capabilities the
protocol version and the client info.
Cool. Now as the MP MCP server you're
going to respond uh and give them your
capabilities your protocol version your
server info and then also your
instructions. That last piece is very
interesting. Um, instructions is a a
string that according to the spec may or
may not get integrated into the system
prompt for the client. Um, which I think
is a really cool opportunity here for
malicious MCP servers to inject uh
instructions into the the context um
that the user will be putting their
prompt. Uh so I think we see a really
good opportunity here for tool hijacking
for malicious NCP servers to control the
context uh the system prompt in specific
um terms here. So um definitely want to
take a a look at that instructions um
response in the um servers
initialization response um and see if
the client is doing something weird with
that instructions uh that you might be
able to utilize as an attacker from the
malicious MCP server perspective. server
info and protocol version are both a
little bit um boring. They just kind of
contain strings or whatever. Um
capabilities here once again is the
primarily um uh interesting component.
So what are some of the capabilities
that we have here? Um we've got logging,
prompts, resources, tools, and I believe
utilities. I might have left that off
that list. Um and obviously the ones
that are most interesting there are
tools and resources with uh prompts and
logging and utilities coming after. Um
so tools of course is what we know most
uh you know we we often think of MCP
servers for they're providing tools to
the MCP client that might be utilized um
in by the LLM um in conjunction with the
user's requests right so this is how you
communicate hey I support tools as an
MCP server um prompts contains like some
prompts that the user might be able to
use some templates that sort of thing um
resources uh it contains
uh some very interesting stuff. I I'll
go ahead and read a direct quote from
the from the spec here. It says, "The
MCP protocol provides a standardized way
for servers to expose resources to the
client. Resources allow servers to share
data that provides context to language
models such as files, database schemas,
application specific information, etc.
Each resource is uniquely identified by
a URI.
Guys, that is so juicy." Okay. So, um if
you are an MCP server, you can
definitely provide those resources. Uh
maybe you could do that maliciously.
We'll talk about that later. Um or if
you are a client, you definitely want to
check and see in your assessing MCP
server what kind of resources the server
supports. And even if it doesn't list
resources here in the um uh
initialization response, it may you may
still be able to use the resources read
um uh RPC call. Who knows? something
good to check. Um, but yeah, that's what
the sort of handshake looks like. Then
it does a notification thing, but
overall it's mostly just initialize from
the client to the server, giving the
capabilities, and initialize from the
server to the client, giving the
capabilities, and then they agree on a
protocol version. Okay, now that we've
covered the initialization flow, let's
go ahead and go into MCP client objects.
Okay, so these are the sort of things
that the client uh is presenting to the
server and that the server may be able
to interact with the client on. Um I
will caveat this by saying that uh a lot
of the MCP clients out there even in
major um programming languages uh you
know the primary library in major
programming languages um they're not
true MCP clients. Um, according to the
spec, MCP clients should actually be MCP
servers as well, you know, that are
creating like a sort of back and forth
communication. Unfortunately, what we
see in a lot of MCP clients, um, is that
the MCP client is just sort of yeeting
messages out and then reading the
response and that's it, you know, and
it's it's looking for that specific
response. It's not like allowing for
ping um actions or anything like that.
uh it's just sort of reading data, you
know, writing data out, reading only
exactly what they want in and not, you
know, presenting anything else. Um so,
or at least that's been my experience in
my limited experience. So, um realize
that you might want to look at the MCP
client that uh you're interacting with
and make sure that they support some of
these compatibilities even from a code
perspective, even if they're turned off
in the compatibilities um uh
initialization.
Um, all right. But let's talk about the
three uh objects in MCP clients. That's
roots, sampling, and elicitation. Okay.
So, roots first is very interesting. Um,
it I'm going to go ahead and read this
again. The model context protocol
provides a standardized way for clients
to expose file system roots to the
server. Hell yes, that is exactly what
we want. Um,
and clients that support roots must
declare those roots during uh
initialization in the compatibilities uh
section. So, you know, maybe it will
support it, maybe it won't, maybe it
will declare it and support it anyway.
Definitely all always good to check. So,
spin up a malicious MCP server if you're
attacking a client and shoot down a
roots list request to see if the client
returns any roots. It'd be super cool if
it just like dropped back uh you know a
root for for slash or something like
that. Um uh and you know speaking of
that our first RPC that we'll cover here
is rootslist. That is what can be sent
from the server to the client to get a
list of the roots that the client
supports. Very cool. Um there's not a
lot of other functionality there. You
can subscribe to root changes. Um but
unfortunately not a lot of information
there. what you might see is some path
leaks or some disclosures that might
give you some good information. Um,
moving from roots to the next objects,
we have sampling. Okay, and sampling is
great because it allows the MCP server
to query the LLM and make uh messages
for the user. Okay, which how could that
possibly go wrong? Um, it could go wrong
really easily actually in a lot of ways.
Um, so yeah, let's go ahead and cover
those. So, you know, let's say we have a
malicious MCP server. Um, they drop back
sampling to the to the user. That
sampling says uh creates a message and
you they can invoke other tools or
things of the like um to attack the
user.
Of course, you know, there's there's
lots of ways that this could could
happen. Um they could trigger uh
resource exhaustion by calling other
tools perhaps um if they're able to just
spin a message back out that gets
processed. Um, there's tons of things
that could happen here and I'll go ahead
and put up a picture on the screen now.
Um, it's it's a sort of an alert from
the protocol. It says for trust and
safety and security, there should always
be a human in the loop with the ability
to deny sampling requests. Applications
should provide UI that makes it easy and
intuitive to review sampling requests.
Allows users to view and edit prompts
before sending. Present generated
response for review before delivery.
This is the same sort of thing they put
in the tools section. And we all know
that the user doesn't always approve
tools before they are invoked. So I
definitely think we'll see scenarios
where MCP servers are able to just yeet
messages back to the client and have
those processed and analicious MCP
server may be able to invoke tools on a
different um MCP server uh or incur you
know negative effect to the victim that
way. Um so that's something to be
thinking about. Uh I know that sampling
and elicitation which is what we'll
cover next are relatively new to the
protocol. So um I think this is
something we might be a little bit fast
on but something to be aware of uh for
sure. Um I also wanted to mention here
that even if there is a prompt to have
the user approve you know the MCP
servers modified message or whatever. Um
then we can also use invisible prompt
smuggling here right using um invisible
unicode characters. Um alla embrace the
red um and reszo. Uh, and I think that
would also uh introduce a lot of client
side UI vulnerabilities that could allow
you to have get in um a prompt injection
which could be the start of a chain of
delivery which is important for AI
vulnerabilities. Just a thought. Okay.
Next is um elicitation. This allows the
MCP server to request information from
the user. Okay. Uh once again, another
great spot for um injections, whether it
be uh XSS, uh something of the like
there. But I love the trust and safety
and security uh announcement that they
put on this part of the of the protocol.
It says um uh servers must not use
elicitation to request sensitive
information from the user. Must not do
that, guys. Seriously, guys, don't do
that. Please don't do that. Yeah, that's
exactly what we're going to do. Um so
very interesting uh sort of
functionality here for attackers that
are in the malicious MCP server
perspective. Um I think that there will
also be situations where there will be
no user interaction elicitation requests
where the server will request a piece of
information from the client and the
client will say, "Oh, I've got that, you
know, in my little environment store or
something like that. Let me just
helpfully give this to the MCP server
without prompting the user." That's
definitely going to happen at some
point. So, um, be on the lookout for
that. Um, auto accepting those
elicitation requests. Um, the available
actions for elicitation requests are
accept, decline, and cancel. Each one of
those have nuances that I'm not going to
get into here on this podcast, but know
that elicitation, should uh your um
client support it, is a very powerful
tool that you could use to get um some
data on the victim or even invoke
delivery for a prompt injection chain.
All right. So, that covers clients. Um,
next we'll go ahead and talk about MCP
servers. Okay. Um, the I'm only going to
actually talk about two of the objects
uh on MCP servers. I'm going to leave
the utilities and prompts and other ones
to you. I'm going to talk to you about
tools and resources. And guys, actually,
the model context protocol spec is very
consumable. So, I would encourage you to
go read it if you have uh, you know, if
your interest was piqued by this
podcast. Okay? Or at least when you inc
uh you know encounter an MCP server or
client in the future um you know where
to go and just know it's not very
intimidating. It can take very long to
get through it. Um
and you've got this podcast now to be
your guide. Um so definitely should be
much more approachable for you. Okay. So
uh MCP servers expose tools and
resources. Let's talk about tools first.
Tools are the object that of course we
all kind of think of MCP servers for. Um
they expose tool definitions to the user
and give the ability to call these tools
um to the MCP client uh that can be
utilized at will um to in invoke these
in and um in pursuit of the user's
intents right uh intent intents is what
I was trying to say there. Um so that is
done via uh a sequence of RPC calls and
the client sends a tool list call to the
server and the server will respond with
these various definitions for the tools.
Okay. And um here's what that schema
looks like. The tool object sche excuse
me tool object schema contains name,
title, description, input schema, output
schema, and annotation. So there's a lot
of uh really interesting stuff here, but
the first thing that I want to point out
to you is that we have both name and
title. And if you look at the annotation
spec, we also have a title for the tool
inside of the annotation. So there's
three places where you can potentially
name a tool. And that's not even talking
about namespaces, which is a pivotal
part of MC uh MCP security because
namespaces are what prevents name
collisions when you have multiple MCP
servers with the same tool name. Okay.
So, I don't know how they heck this up.
Like, it is one of the most essential
pieces, one of the only pieces of MCP
that is important, which is what tool
are we calling. And somehow there's like
six ways to define what tool is being
displayed versus what's being called,
and it just makes for a whole pooa.
Okay. Um, so definitely look at name,
title, and annotation title at least um
when you're looking at how tools are
being represented to the user and which
um sort of name is being used to invoke
the tool in the back end. And there the
difference between those two things
could result in a massive difference for
the user. Um because you may be able to
name your tool super great everything
you know amazing awesome always use me
tool um you know in the name but the
title is what's being displayed to the
to the user and uh there creates a
mismatch there. They're like oh I think
I'm enabling you know Justin's cool fun
tool but actually I'm enabling evil tool
that is used for everything. always use
this tool always, you know, um and and
that may sway the um MCP server uh or
the MCP client to uh select or the LLM
to select to use that tool. Hope that
makes sense. Um there's input and output
schema which there's definitely some
interesting attack vectors in those that
I would encourage you to go look at. I'm
not going to cover those right now, but
I did find some interesting stuff in
those. Um, and description is also
pivotal because that's where you can dis
describe the tool. Now, if this
description is being embedded directly
into the system prompt, then we kind of
open ourselves up for some malicious MCP
server um tool hijacking or tool
poisoning attacks. Um, so be be aware of
how the tool definitions are being um
integrated into the um the client side
there.
Um and then finally when the client
decides to call the the tool um the
client will send the tool call RPC
request with the requisite um
information um and that will invoke the
the call um and the input you know will
be defined by the input schema etc. Um
and tools then can respond with uh
structured or unstructured data. Here
are some of the awesome types that uh
the MCP server can respond with. Okay,
we've got text image which so we've got,
you know, B 64 encoded image data um via
the data attribute in the image. We've
got audio data also B 64 encoded. Um
we've got resource links which include a
URI and a MIME type as well. Um, and
each of these also have annotations
which add different um, sort of spins on
what's being represented to the user
there. Um, very interesting. Um, and
then there's also structured data that
that comes back from the call um, per
the schema. Um, so very very cool
opportunity here to respond with various
resources and then see how those
resources are being rendered on the MCP
client and see if you can incur some
vulnerabilities here. This is kind of
giving um some uh end to-end encrypted
communication vibe uh you know on like a
chat app or something where you can
invoke specific you know send like a
something a link that gets converted
into a card and that in that conversion
it triggers like a whole exploit chain
something like that right is kind of
what I'm thinking here um for the
malicious MCP server um to attack the
client so what are some of the foot guns
here with um tools uh obviously tool
names are very ambiguous we already
talked about that. Look for collisions.
Look for namespace hide or um uh tool
hijacking. Look for namespace
collisions. Um one of the things that's
really interesting is the spec is not
clear about how namespaces are supposed
to be defined. So you know the name of
the server
tool name creates like the full name.
But what if the tool name contains
underscore underscore? Well then you can
have a collision, right? So just be
thinking about how the full I guess
fully qualified tool name is being um uh
constructed and with a namespace or not
with a namespace um and try to utilize
the discrepancies between those to in
invoke um your malicious tool tool
hijacking or cause DOSs or something
like that. Interesting stuff. Um let's
see what else did I have here that was
interesting. Yeah, of course, you know,
trying to use the description field or
the name fields to uh hijack tool calls.
Um,
one of the things that's interesting to
look at is is like user interaction or
user confirmation a tool call because if
it is, then that is, you know, you're
trusting the LLM with making a user
confirmation decision, right? Um, which
is never good. So, that's I think that's
reportable as is. That's just a security
architecture problem. Um uh and then
last but not least um
there's also some attack scenarios here
for MCP proxies that I was going to
mention. Um MCP CP proxies are kind of
like a client server hybrid where you
you can um man I can't talk today. You
get a bunch of uh data from different
MCP servers and you pull them together
and you expose them as one MCP server.
So you're kind of like a client and a
server um al together, right? uh and I
just wanted to say that whenever there's
different LLM providers uh different an
MCP server on one side and then a
different you know client presenting
another server there's layers of
abstraction there um and I've seen DOSs
occur where um some of these servers and
clients are not respecting the uh
required schema for um typing and stuff
like that in these JSON RPC calls uh and
that can incur DOSs so just keep that in
mind as well. Okay, so that is tools.
Hopefully you guys have a ton of attack
vectors to think of there. Um, now we'll
move to resources. And resources is such
an interesting thing because it is end
quote. Uh, the model context protocol
provides a standardized way for servers
to expose resources to the client. And
that can be files, it can be HTTP URLs,
it can be apparently git repos. Um, tons
tons tons of really interesting stuff
here. If I were you and I was an, you
know, a client that got access to an MCP
server, I would immediately look for
resources. I would immediately call
resources list RPC to see if there's any
files or URLs or tokens or additional
contexts that I could download um to
understand more about the MCP server or
to just leak information.
Um, so this is kind of how this works.
The client sends to the server
resources.
The server responds to that with a list
of um resources and then you can do a
resources read RPC call and the
parameter for that is the URI file slash
whatever https slash you know it's just
like freaking arbitrary file read as a
service it feels like okay and then to
make it even better guys so you know
there's definitely the potential for
path reversal there um or like arbitrary
file
Um to make it even better, there's also
templatized resources. Okay, what are
templized resources? Those are available
under resources/templatelist.
Those are resources where there is a
template in the URI.
Okay. And that it takes parameters and
puts them into the URI, right? So this
is like 100% path traversal, like 100%.
Um so anytime you see resources
templates uh or um resources definitely
want to try to go after those to try to
get arbitrary file read. Um and so you
know what will happen then when you do a
resources uh template is it'll
dynamically construct the path using
your variable right um which is just
freaking lovely uh and definitely is
going to incur a ton of vulnerabilities.
I'm like I was sitting over here like
you know
uh so excited about that. Um so
definitely look there and I love the
spec as well. It says okay here are the
file schemes we're going to support
https file and git and it just supports
git. Like it it's listed specifically in
the spec that you should support git. Um
which is amazing because there's a ton
of stuff you can do with git. um you
know you can do uh sub subm module um
recursion attack stuff where you can you
know um uh write to into sim links and
stuff like that write arbitrary files um
you can do use hooks to cause um rce
there's like tons of stuff that you can
do there um very exciting um and
obviously file and hps are just super
interesting for arbitrary file read and
then https it does add this caveat it's
servers should only use this scheme as a
resource when the client is able to
fetch and load the resource directly
from the web on its own. That is, it
doesn't need to read the resource via
the MCP server. Right? So, it's not like
it's not like SSRF quite as much, but I
could definitely see some interesting
client side attacks as well there where
you're providing an HTTPS URL back down
to the client. Um, or if there were
other schemes like JavaScript and then
you provide it back down to the client,
that would also be very interesting,
right? Um,
so those are kind of the things I was
thinking about from resources. Uh,
hopefully you guys understand that how
how tools and resources work. Resources,
I'm not sure I explained the the
response. It mostly just contains like
the mime type and the text uh for the
specific resource response that that you
requested. Um, which is like pretty much
all that you would need. Uh, and of
course the URI is provided uh into
resources read um to select the resource
that you are querying. Um, so lots of
good attack surface there. I definitely
did not think MCP servers were going to
be this juicy. Um, lots of fun here. Uh
and I think it's important to remind you
guys in the audience to always try to
take a very technical approach to um
some of these modern challenges as well
because AI is definitely one of those
areas where you could spend a lot of
time talking to LLMs and trying to
convince them and kind of um using your
soft soft hacking skills uh there. But
um I guess underneath the hood there is
also a lot of really juicy technically
complex uh attack surface that you could
go after. Um so you know spin up your
own MCP servers uh write your own
malicious MCP client and uh maybe you'll
see the vulnerability start falling out.
Um all right that's all I had. Hopefully
you guys liked this. Give me your
feedback. I expect a couple comments and
corrections uh because I'm not that um
proficient with this protocol. So, uh,
if I made a mistake on MCP protocol
stuff anywhere, please comment in the
corrections, uh, um, channel in Discord
to set the record straight and win
yourself some, uh, some internet points
and my eternal thanks. Um, all right,
that's a wrap on the pod this week,
y'all. Peace.
And that's a wrap on this episode of
Critical Thinking. Thanks so much for
watching to the end, y'all. If you want
more critical thinking content, uh, or
if you want to support the show, head
over to ctbb.show/isord.
You can hop in the community. There's
lots of great highlevel hacking
discussion happening [music] there on
top of master classes, hackalongs,
exclusive content, and a full-time
hunters guild if you're a full-time
hunter. It's a great time, trust me. All
right, I'll see you there.